A Guide to the Pulaski Iron Company Title Abstracts, 1910-1918
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University
Pulaski Iron Company Title Abstracts 1910-1918
Special Collections, Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms94-025
3 containers; 1.2 cu. ft.
Title abstracts for various properties conveyed to the Pulaski Iron Company in Augusta, Botetourt, Pulaski, Roanoke and Wythe counties, Virginia.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Pulaski Iron Company Title Abstracts were purchased by Special Collections in two lots. The first four volumes were purchased in 1994; the fifth volume, containing abstracts to the Biggs and Hamlett tracts in Roanoke County, was purchased in 2008.
Historical Information
The Pulaski Iron Company was incorporated in 1884. Commencing operation in 1888, the company's furnace was Southwest Virginia's first modern pig iron blast furnace. Known locally as "PI," the company at its peak in 1907 produced an average of about 150 tons of iron per day. The furnace continued in operation until the Great Depression, with the exception of an 8-month stoppage in 1916. John W. Eckman served as the company's general manager for many years.
Scope and Content
This collection contains abstracts of title prepared for the Pulaski Iron Company on properties conveyed to the company in Augusta, Botetourt, Pulaski, Roanoke and Wythe counties, Virginia, during the early twentieth century. The collection is comprised of four bound volumes and one unbound volume. Compiled by William B. Kegley, a Wytheville, Virginia attorney, each volume contains typescript copies of land grants, deeds, surveys, wills, other legal documents and correspondence relating to individual tracts.
Included are documents relating to the purchase of the Cloverdale iron property in Botetourt County from the Tredegar Company; the Wood tract and the Arcadia tracts of the Virginia Lumber and Extract Company (also in Botetourt County); the Shelton property (Augusta County); the Feather, J. E. Biggs, and J. G. Hamlett tracts in Roanoke County; the Wythe County property of Franklin Carter; and property in Pulaski County from Oscar Laughon, T. W. Kersey and G. C. Hall.
Arrangement
The documents within the volumes retain their original order, with each volume being indexed. As most of the volumes are bound and contain materials relating to more than one property over a period of years, the volumes could not be arranged in any specific order. A generally chronological order is followed, with the exception of the title abstract for the Wood tract.
Contents List
- [Book 1] (Box-folder 1-1)
  - J. E. Biggs tract 1911
  - J. G. Hamlett tract 1911
- [Book 2] (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Cloverdale iron property (v.1) 1913-1915
- [Book 3] (Box-folder 2-1)
  - Cloverdale iron property (v.2) 1913-1915
  - Wood tract 1910-1911
- [Book 4] (Box-folder 2-2)
  - Arcadia tracts 1915-1917
  - Shelton property 1916-1917
  - Feather property 1917
- [Book 5] (Box-folder 3-1)
  - Franklin Carter property 1917-1918
  - Oscar Laughon property 1918
  - T. W. Kersey and G. C. Hall property 1918